On the path to spatial intelligence,
generating pixels that are truly
spatially contextualized and grounded,
that is the very hard step that Atlas
has taken.
>> You know, LLMs are built on next token
prediction. We've seen video models as
being built on next frame prediction.
Atlas is really new view prediction.
>> This is the real place where AI can
actually unlock a ton of value for
people and their process. We're saying
like 50, 100 extra reduction. There's a
famous shot in the first Matrix movie
where Neo is like falling down. Exactly.
They had hundreds of cameras doing that
angle on a green screen. With Atlas, we
can do this with just three cameras. No
studio capture, no green screen, no
expensive calibration.
>> No one has ever seen these results.
>> When you set out to do this, did you
know it was going to work?
>> I was pretty sure. Each time we made the
model bigger, and each time we trained
it for longer, it got significantly
better.
>> Does that mean we're going to get 4D
video? Can I go walk around?
>> So, big day yesterday, you launched a
new frontier model, which has got
amazing reception, which is still coming
in. I think maybe a good way to
structure this conversation, let's just
talk about exactly what that was, and
then we'll go back to history and work
our way back up. So, maybe Justin, do
you want to talk about what was launched
yesterday, why it's significant.
>> Yeah, so Atlas is our new next
generation world model. Um, it has three
basic things. It can generate,
reconstruct, and simulate the world. Um,
so within that, there's a couple
different major capabilities. It has
really good camera condition generation.
So, you can input an image together with
a camera trajectory with a camera
trajectory and steer the model and have
it generate, you know, video frames
along any any perspective you want. It's
really good at sparse 3D reconstruction.
You can input one or multiple up to 100
frames, um, that are views of the real
world, and use those to reconstruct the
real world. And that reconstruction can
take the case either of of novel of
video flying through the space, or an
explicit 3D reconstruction of the space.
Um, then finally, it can be used for
simulation. Um, and for this, we show
off, um, you know, these awesome bullet
time videos, which got a lot of
attention online, and then also robotics
simulation.
>> What's a What's a bullet time video?
>> A bullet time video, this comes from the
Matrix. You know, there there's a famous
shot in the first Matrix movie where Neo
is like falling down.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Exactly. So, and then remember in that
famous shot he's like falling down, it's
in slow motion, and the camera flies all
the way around. Um so, that's the way
that they did that shot is they had a
ring of like hundreds of cameras. So,
then like he fell over in the studio,
they had hundreds of cameras viewing
that angle on a green screen, and then
they used those hundreds and hundreds of
cameras to make that that famous shot in
in Matrix. But now with Atlas we can do
this with just as few as through three
cameras. So, like no studio capture, no
green screen, no expensive calibration.
We can literally stick like three
cameras on three iPhones on tripods, um
use these to take sort of a video of
something happening, um like someone
shooting a basket, someone dropping a
strawberry into a bowl of milk. And then
from those three like iPhone videos, we
can then reframe the shot, and imagine
like a like freeze time, have the camera
fly in like as the milk is splashing up,
and get these amazing frozen time views.
Um and we can do this with just uh just
a couple cameras.
>> Can Can you um just maybe What is the
simplest description of what Atlas does?
Like what goes in and what comes out?
>> Yeah, so one of the one of the really
core principles of Atlas, like the most
fundamental thing, is it does new view
prediction. Um and this is a a really
fundamental primitive that we think is
super exciting, a super new primitive
for for base models that no one's ever
done before. Right? So, we know LLMs are
built on next token prediction, we've
seen video models as being built on next
frame prediction. Atlas is really new
view prediction. Right? That given some
number of views of a scene or a
description of a scene, um those go into
what we call a spatial context that
describes implicitly what is the world
that we want to talk about, then you can
point a virtual camera at at an
arbitrary point in space and time, and
Atlas will understand what that world is
supposed to look like from that position
in space and time.
>> You know, you know, Ben, that you know,
with with a with a bajillion video
models out there all claiming to be
world models and all claiming to have
novel views, and
can you maybe tease apart
can more concretely how this is
different from like the myriad models
that have come before?
>> Mhm. Yeah, I think what Justin was
saying about the spatial context aspect
is super important here. So there's many
video models, a lot of video models
actually got their claim to fame from
their single dimension input or their
start to last frame interpolation. Now
we're starting to see models that can do
this kind of omni referencing with, you
know, 20, 30, 50 images. But what's key
with Atlas is that it actually has a
kind of like specially grounded meaning
to every frame you put into it. So it's
not just an image that the model's going
to interpret whatever way it wants or
you can kind of try to argue with it in
the the text prompting and get it to do
something specific. With Atlas, every
image actually has an associated
three-dimensional camera pose and that
means that you can perform this task of
reconstruction with an extremely high
degree of precision, right? So if we had
four views of this room, one at each
corner, you can put those into the model
and then get an exact replication of
everything you see in this room and it's
not going to guess what's in the other
corner, like the relationship between
things. It's just going to reproduce
exactly what you give it. And you can
also do that in a kind of creative or
imaginative sense, too. If you take two
photos from different, you know, AI
generations or real-world locations, you
can actually position and stage those to
build these kind of intentionally
directed fly-throughs that are really
governed by exactly the precise place
that you put the content you want and
where the camera's going to look and
travel,
which is very different, I think, than
the kind of like more slot machine
effect you get of having to retry
generations over and over with just that
kind of higher level of text control you
get with video models.
>> Is this just kind of an obvious,
you know, scaled-up version of a
traditional video model or is it a new
architecture?
>> I think it's it's a pretty new thing for
a couple of different reasons.
One that we talk about is it does both
generation and reconstruction jointly in
the same model. Like Ben was saying,
this thing can take a couple of views of
this room and then reconstruct
everything in this room exactly as you
see it. And historically, reconstruction
has been its own subfield in computer
vision with its own specialized task,
its own specialized models. And
generation is what all the text all the
text to video models are really good at
like what all the all the big diffusion
models we've seen the last couple years.
And those are great for creative
applications. I want to imagine
something that's never been there
before. Um but now with Atlas for the
first time we're putting these two
different parts of visual intelligence
together in one model. So it can do both
3D reconstruction and generation
together in one architecture. So to do
that we had to make a couple changes. Um
one is we had to make it multimodal from
the start. So this thing natively works
on text, it works on images, it works on
videos. It also works on camera poses um
as a native input to the model which I
don't think anyone's ever done at the
pre-training phase before. Um and it
uses um it uses 3D as a native modality
that it works on. So this thing from the
beginning was designed to be natively
multimodal in a way that no one else I
think
>> Sorry, I just um
I don't know this space super well but
3D is this like depth or models and like
what is that what is that mean?
>> Yeah, so the formulation we used so far
is depth maps.
>> Okay.
>> Right? So um right now you can have a
when you have a frame that has a a a
virtual camera telling its position in
3D space, yeah, that camera position and
and camera parameters are a native input
to the model. And then what attached to
that camera position you can have both
um like RGB telling you what is that
what is that position in space look like
and you can have a depth map that tells
you what is the spatial structure of
that position in 3D space. So then you
know text, image, video, 3D cameras are
these modalities that this thing all
does jointly in a multimodal way.
>> I want to add something cuz I think what
Justin just said is actually so
important and also what Ben said that
it's under appreciated. It's the first
time we have a unification of pixel
generation and pixel reconstruction. In
the world of computer vision this field
has been around for more than half a
century.
Um
sitting here having been in this field
for decades, I cannot tell you how many
PhD thesis have been written on the
problem of reconstruction or novel view
things synthesis and also
our field traditionally
uh have multiple tracks. You go to a
computer vision conference, you have the
pixel generation track, you have some
recognition track and you have 3D
reconstruction track. This is a elegant
model that combines
or unifies the problem of reconstruction
and generation by anchoring on
viewpoints and the the viewpoint
estimation and
that's just incredibly powerful.
>> Can Can you Can you maybe
Well, can we take a step back and then
maybe you just fill something out? So,
when when you started the company, I
remember you saying uh you know, you
want to tackle
um spatial intelligence, right? And uh
you know, now we have this new model.
And so, it feel I mean, like as a
layperson, it feels very general to me.
You've got next product prediction and
this is next new view prediction.
>> New view prediction, right?
>> So, like you can get one view out of a
set of views and you have a new view.
Can maybe you pencil out like like how
this is a significant step to this
general problem of spatial intelligence?
And maybe by like starting to describe
what spatial intelligence is?
>> Well, spatial intelligence eventually
must enable us to
both generate what the space is, reason
within it, and being able to edit and
interact within it.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, we can argue is it 3D or 4D?
Ultimately, it's 4D with the time
dimension, but even just 3D, these are
the fundamental tasks that one has to do
or spatial intelligence has to enable.
And then we talk about with that, you
can render, you can simulate, and you
can plan actions. But to do that, a
fundamental problem to solve is to
understand the geometry and structure
and the physics of the space.
>> Yeah.
>> And I do believe Atlas is a significant
step forward because now with every
single frame, you have a
you can generate an estimate a important
piece of information, which is the the
view viewpoint, the camera pose. And
that is the most critical information
one needs about the geometry of the of
the space. And that can lead to all the
emergent behaviors we see in our
in the downstream of the model, which we
showed in the blog. So
So in the on the path to spatial
intelligence,
generating pixels is definitely a a
early step, which we have seen with what
you call it gazillions of models. But
generating pixels that are truly
spatially contextualized and grounded is
absolutely another major step. And that
is the very hard step that Atlas has
taken.
I we definitely have, you know, we can
just
keep going here, right? Like there is
the fourth dimension of time, which will
bring in dynamics. And there is more
higher fidelity simulation and
delineation of the space. So this is
part of the the road map of spatial
intelligence.
>> Great, yeah. I mean, I definitely want
to like dig into like where this is
going. But first, maybe let's talk about
getting here.
How long has World Models been in
existence?
>> Two and a half Two and a half, yeah.
>> And so you you've actually released
models before. So what why didn't you
just jump right to Atlas?
>> [laughter]
>> Good question.
>> It's so magic, right? Yeah.
>> Justin's team needs a lot of chips.
>> Yeah, we need a lot of GPUs to actually
[laughter] scale this thing up.
So what one of the last year we released
our Marble World model, and that was the
first kind of big major World model that
we put out. That that powers our current
Marble product. And Marble and Marble is
really cool. Marble can take images, it
can take videos, it can take text
prompts, and use these to generate 3D
worlds. But one of the biggest
differences between Marble and Atlas is
exactly what is that output modality.
So, marble was really focused on
Gaussian splats as an output
representation. So, whatever you're
inputting, um it's going to output a 3D
world represented as a as a Gaussian
splat. And Gaussian splats are really
useful, right? They're really nice,
they're easy to render, they are they
they can they can render efficiently on
mobile devices, on VR devices, they can
interoperate with other with a with game
engines, with simulation engines.
There's a lot of nice things about
Gaussian splats. But, you know, I think
that was kind of a bottleneck in the
previous marble model. So, what we did
with Atlas is redesign the thing bit. Um
and we realized that we need to
bifurcate these modalities earlier and
actually have these things all these
modalities working in a more unified way
in the model. So, now with Atlas, um the
the the fundamental primitive is not
like a good generate a Gaussian splat
world. The fundamental primitive is is
as we said new view prediction. Um and
that can generate RGB frames, that can
generate 3D, and we can use those to
generate a beautiful Gaussian splat
worlds when you need them. Um but, we
don't need to bottleneck our our our
outputs through the Gaussian splats when
we don't need to. And that was a that
actually took a lot of, you know, blood,
sweat, and tears to understand like what
are all the pros and cons of these
different representations. So, that's
one part of it. Um the other part is you
got to like climb the scaling ladder,
right? You got to like work your way up
and like do smaller experiments, do
smaller models like to build your
conviction on what's going to work and
what's going to scale. Um and there's
there's you know, if you could instantly
know the right thing that's going to
scale, you know, you should just do
that. But, when we when we started
[laughter] the company, the world was a
very different place. Like there's
there's no scaling law of special
intelligence. Right. So, like when we
started the company, like the world was
in a very different place, the tech was
in a very different place. We had a lot
of ambitions for where we wanted it to
go, but it took a couple it took a a
couple iterations for us to hit upon
this formulation that we thought is
actually is actually like this is the
one. This is this is the one that can
scale out.
>> You know, Ben,
you know, being the creator of Nerf and
doing a lot of 3D and reconstruction, so
it's not so obvious to me that like if
you have multiple views that you
actually end up with a 3D thing. But,
like you've kind of like made a career
of ending up with a 3D thing. So, maybe
talk a little bit about like kind of
that step.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um yeah, I mean as you said,
I've spent many, many years of my career
as a mass majority of my career actually
working on producing 3D things from
images.
Um and this is actually something we we
talked about a lot early on in the
company even of like is this going to be
the approach that produces 3D, right?
Are we going to synthesize multiple
views and then build 3D out of that? Are
we going to try to go direct to 3D? Like
there's been a lot of um uncertainty in
the field around like which of those
approaches kind of will win out or will
kind of like reap the best advantages
earlier on. Um but I did have a lot of
conviction just from seeing
the kind of power of what I would almost
call the brute force scaling scaling at
a very, very, very small baby scale, not
like real model scaling, but the scaling
of dense reconstruction that we had seen
happening over the past 3 years before.
Um so, basically we put up
>> What Why is dense reconstruction Yeah.
dense?
>> Yeah, dense.
>> Dense dense is
>> Because I know we're going to talk about
sparse and I want to make sure that
people understand what is dense and what
is sparse.
>> Yeah, so I think this is actually even
on the kind of like business and
commercial side I I think been one of
the challenges of productizing uh 3D
reconstruction technology like at a
fundamental level, right? People kind of
don't
uh
in in a in a casual sense like you think
I took three photos of this object or I
took six photos of this room. Like I I
look at the photos, I can understand in
my mind like how this piece together. I
can kind of fill in the gaps and get it,
but there's just never been really any
kind of reconciliation between those
like really data-driven priors and then
the kind of brute force dense
reconstruction, which it actually is
much more akin to almost like scientific
or medical imaging what we did in dense
reconstruction, right? You basically
have to say every single thing I want to
appear in this reconstruction, I need at
least three or four views of it. And if
you think about that, like even just in
this room, right? There's like under the
microphone, under the table, between
every different crack and crevice and
the plant leaves, right? To actually
truly get a picture that covers every
one of those spots, it's this like very
tedious and exhaustive effort to walk
around the room. I think you've all seen
me running around various places like
capturing them. It takes, you know, for
for someone who's well-trained per se,
like it can take minutes, but if you
hand a casual consumer or even some like
kind of professional trying to do this
for the first time,
an average
like cell phone camera or capture
device, like it's going to take them
probably an hour. I've seen someone for
the first time trying to scan a
multi-room environment spend like two
hours walking through it and get enough
coverage. And that's just this like
very, very exhaustive and tedious loop.
And so yeah, when we say dense, we
really mean dense. It's like this room I
want
>> You just need like lots of
>> so many photos, right? I want like 100,
200, 300 photos of this room to to
capture it. And what we're trying to do
is bring that down to like three.
>> Three.
>> Right? Well, we're saying like 50, 100 x
reduction. And then that's at that scale
where it just completely like flips that
calculus on its head of like what type
of captures you reconstruct. You can go
back to existing imagery you have. You
can go to stuff you find on the internet
and even build scenes out of that. You
can go to casual videos and like kind of
unearth a lot of footage in the past you
would never have treated as
reconstructible and go back and like
bring it to life as 3D potentially. This
is something we've been playing around
with a lot with Atlas, right? Like
taking old clips. Like I've taken a
bunch of my own old captures that never
worked before and then put them through
the system and I kind of seen a
reconstruction for the first time or
taken my old captures and thrown away
95% of the photos I took and you know,
imagine angles that I never would have
gotten from a traditional kind of like
Nerfer Splat type reconstruction.
>> One thing that's under appreciated on
the website of the demos is the Stanford
demo where
Ben showed uh
anywhere between 3 to 25 images you can
reconstruct that entire Stanford quad.
But the thing is we had to show it from
aerial view. But every single input
image is been standing on the ground
taking a picture from the ground. So,
everything you see are generated but
according to the laws of reconstruction.
And this is really magical.
>> And this is where like generation and
reconstruction need to interplay in a
really fundamental way to solve this
problem. Because under the classic kind
of reconstruction stuff that Ben was
talking about, like the reason you need
so many views is because I need like
multiple images and I need to
triangulate this point in 3D space and
see it from multiple viewpoints. So,
that means like that's required in the
traditional version. And on the flip
side, anything that wasn't captured in
these views, like any pixel that was not
visible in one of the input views will
be a hole in a 3D reconstruction.
Because fundamentally like if a thing
wasn't visible in the input views, you
know, you need to imagine it to fill in
the gaps. And that's fundamentally a
generative process. So, even in this
room, even if we set Ben loose with a
DSLR and like let him like capture like
hundreds of views of this room, even the
world expert on doing these dense
captures is still going to miss some
spots. Like he's not going to get like
underneath all of the microphones or
underneath all the tables or like in
between all the chair legs, you're
always going to miss something, no
matter how many views you get. So, that
that's where you need generation as
another mechanism in the model. Because
you're never going to get everything.
So, you need to have some generative
capacity for the model to imagine, oh,
based on what I'm seeing, then like
first triangulate what I what I can see,
but then fill in the gaps of the stuff
that inevitably inevitably was not
captured.
>> Yeah, and there's something like super
cool about this that LLMs have really
understood this for a for a long time,
right? There was kind of one of these
like context wars like the first couple
years I was like, oh, we got to 128 to
256 to like 512. We got a million,
right? And everyone kind of understands
now at a pretty tangible level the value
of, you know, you crank your context
length to high when you're using your
coding models. It's a hard problem. Like
everyone has a feel for that. But like
no one has pushed that at all on the
image and video model side in the same
kind of like principled way. Like no
one's out there trying to like put a
like an hour-long video through and do a
needle in a haystack retrieval of like a
frame at the 30 37-minute mark. Whereas
with reconstruction and generation, you
actually have the same exact thing of
like reconstruction is just like
generation with a really long context
and you put a lot of stuff in it. Right?
Like that's the way to actually build
this continuum where you kind of bridge
between those two things. And like
Atlas, like being able to like this is
something we could never do with Marvel.
Marvel had this kind of fundamental
blocker of like you couldn't really jam
more than honestly like a couple images
in. But Atlas, I can go and I can
actually take like a 64-image capture
and do like a fly-through of an entire
house and everything is grounded by
being, you know, seen or like almost
seen or like slightly extrapolated from
what's not there. But you're just
getting these, you know, I'm taking
captures I did with 2,000 images of a
multi-room house and taking it down to
like 30, 40 inputs and the fly-through
looks like basically the same. And this
is just like totally inconceivable
before and it's all enabled by building
this gracefully scaling kind of context
window that you can dump stuff into.
>> And so the way to think about it is like
the the sparseness
are the pictures that you physically
took and then Atlas is a model creates
the rest of the views and then you use
classic reconstruction techniques. Is
that roughly the way to think about it
or
>> In some sense, yeah, yeah. I mean,
that's the beauty of Atlas is like you
can take however many inputs you have
down to like a single view and then you
can always use Atlas as this this
rendering engine to produce anything
else you want. Right? You can you can
navigate it like a virtual camera. Yeah,
exactly. You can just you can say like,
"Okay, I have a picture here. I want a
picture there, there, there." You can
make a couple of those then you can say
to dense fly-through. You can do this in
sequence because it's an auto regressive
model. It's up to you, right, to kind of
pick and choose what you add
interactively into the context as you
generate.
>> I mean, the thing that I just blows my
mind is Listen, I just have a very
simple mental mental model. I I I I four
pictures and then I've got to like have
the model extrapolate
between them and then it has to fit when
you reconstruct. Like it's got to be 3D.
Like and I always think of these
diffusion models as like being visually
great but not accurate. And so like
And and I don't even know if there's a
question here, but like how how how is I
like the room fits? So like how is it
that it's three 3D consistent? Is it
just lots of data or
>> Yeah, I mean it's a part partially it's
a belief in the scaling hypothesis,
right? Like, you know,
>> Did you By the way, but I have to ask,
when you set out to do this, did you
know it was going to work?
>> I was pretty sure.
>> [laughter]
>> Were you sure?
>> I think three of us have total
conviction about the scaling law. That
that I think we do. I do think the exact
architecture choices and data mixtures
is where the the devils are in the
details. I, you know, have
watched Justin and his team going from
we really don't know how long this is
going to take to oh, maybe sign of life
to wow, this is going to work. So it it
no one what no one has done it, but I
think the hypothesis, two hypothesis,
one is scaling law hypothesis, the other
one is next viewpoint prediction. We had
conviction of these two things
primarily.
>> So I think I was very convicted that it
was going to work. I was not sure it was
going to work at this well at this fast,
right? Like I thought there's a chance
that we do this. Maybe it's not clear
that like the first cycle of
pre-training a new model with a new
architecture and a new paradigm. Like
the first cycle of that working is
insane. So I thought there was a chance
in which we had to we might have had to
do a couple more turns of that of that
pre-training cycle before we got to the
level of quality we we wanted.
>> Is there is it are we kind of like at
the end of like the scaling for this
architecture approach? We need another
breakthrough or is there
>> No, no, we're at the beginning.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Without without changing the
architecture?
>> Yeah, we're basically at the beginning.
I think we're basically at the beginning
and we're basically limited by compute
at this point. All right, like data is
is important as Feifei likes to point
out, but like everything has a
bottleneck and I think the main
bottleneck on continuing to scale this
thing is actually training compute.
Right? Like during development, we
trained a sequence of models. We wrote
about this in the blog post a little
bit, but we trained a couple of models
that like the first couple of runs of
the scaling ladder. Um and each time we
made the model bigger and each time we
trained it for longer, each time we put
it on more chips, like it got
significantly better. And the model size
that we like the model that we showed in
the blog post is obviously the biggest
and best one that we trained, but the
thing that was limiting it was not the
scale or the data or anything like that.
It was literally like we had a deadline
of when we wanted to release this thing
and therefore we backed up what we could
afford to train in time for that
deadline.
>> But here's a little bit of a insider
story, right? Like Justin and team are
are training from the smaller and
slightly bigger, you know, are train
having these roadmaps.
And then there was one day in summer,
early summer, that it's not even this
the current Atlas model size, it's a
smaller model. And then Ben, Justin, Ben
feeded into, you know, the viewpoint
generation. And remember that famous
table, the garden table for Nerf paper
and many papers, that
overnight I got a slack. I mean, we all
saw the slack from Ben that our camera
flew through under the table.
>> With the soccer ball.
>> Uh yes, with the soccer ball.
>> ball emergent or is that in the original
picture?
>> It's It's It was real, right?
>> Okay.
>> That morning the three of us looked at
each other in the eyes and say, "That's
it. This is
We're going to build this." Like we we
made a decision within 5 seconds. How
This is just a
no one has ever seen this result.
>> Ben, um
can you talk through maybe more
specifically the use cases? So so
uh World Labs has historically had a lot
of users that were creatives and they
use it for like consistency in, you
know, like whatever 2D images and for
movies and for 3D and for games etc. And
so maybe can you talk about how this
extends use cases or cater to the
existing ones and then we'll I'd like to
talk about robotics actually.
>> Yeah, sure.
Um yeah, I mean it's kind of funny
actually one of the kind of main ways we
even saw people using Marvel plays
exactly into this new view prediction
case. Like a lot of our
>> Marvel being the previous sorry our
Marvel our previous product.
>> Um like people would take that product,
put an image in, get a full 3D scene as
a Gaussian splat, take a couple of
screenshots of it from different points
of view and leave. Right? And we're like
We can just make these images [laughter]
and that's generative AI cool, right? So
So I think like and you know, there's a
lot of degradation there. They're like,
"Oh, this splat could look better." And
it's like, "Okay, what if we just
generatively model those viewpoints with
that exact modality of control?" So I
think like even that core capability of
just like view synthesis, um it's sort
of been this academic problem for a long
time. But in the sense of "Oh, you're
going to do this really dense capture."
Like like generative view synthesis is a
relatively quite a new problem. And we
just see so many people who
uh in this creative pipeline, right?
People have a multi-stage workflow,
right? I don't think there's a single
person out there using one monolithic
model, not even C dance or whatever for
for their entire task. Uh people will
have this like, you know, kind of a
bunch of storyboards and mood boards of
images they pull out from like their
favorite collection of image models. And
then they'll go to different video tools
and like build those together as
keyframes. Then they'll go and like clip
and edit those later, right? So we were
seeing this like sort of, you know,
niche but very specific use case for
Marvel as just providing that like
sanity that you can ground your
generations in some kind of 3D
consistent world, right? People, you
know, I don't I I fought with with
various image models to ask them to like
give me different viewpoints of a room.
And every time you can just look and
see, "Oh, things kind of moved around.
Like it's not stable." And like even
that one seed of a use case I think kind
of signals that there's this value and
there's hiding under the surface there.
Like there's just decades of people
being used to persistent 3D state like
virtually modeling what they would be
doing in the real world and having, you
know, a stage and props and like
elements there, whether it is for a
movie or a show or a marketing shot or
like building out game environments.
Like this this statefulness and
persistence is so key in how people
think about spatial reasoning and like
developing an environment over time.
Like people don't think in this
ephemeral like generate a thing,
generate a thing, like just throw it
away, keep my text prompts. Like people
want to build this like collection of
assets and like model a world in that
way. So we're we're trying to provide
like again with with the spatial context
mechanism and other things like we're
trying to provide that level of control
and precision
and the ability to adjust different
modalities of input starting with the
post images, but you know, we want to
give people more control over the
elements of the things in the scenes
they're looking at and editing and
interaction and all that as we go
forward. And I think that that it
unlocks like further use cases in those
areas we're already seeing, but
also expanding out into kind of any
place people want to create a virtual
replication or or like, you know, a
pre-imagination of a real-world space
they need to build, right? For
architecture and construction. Like I
talked to a guy at some point building
booths for conferences, right? There's
just so many things in the world you
don't think about need to be fabricated
and every single one of those basically
goes through this like pretty
painstaking virtual design phase. And of
that process like the part where you go
into 3D software is kind of one of the
most like arduous and like
labor-intensive parts right now. Like
like taking feedback on a 3D design from
kind of like verbal commentary or sketch
or really really quick
stuff you got from like a creative
director or like a design director or an
architect or whatever. Like mapping that
back into the 3D representation is like
95% of the work, right? You can have a
meeting get feedback and then you go
back and do a week of revisions. And
that's just because like our software is
kind of decades old at this point and
it's it's just never became as intuitive
as, you know, playing with Legos or like
pottery or doing this stuff with your
hands or sketching with a pencil. And
this is the real place where AI can
actually unlock a ton of value for
people in their process, whether it's a
creative application or something more
industrial or design or whatever. Uh,
and that like really motivates me to
kind of build different flavors of of
our model to cater to those kind of
people.
>> Yeah, I I I can understand how it helps
with the creatives cuz like Marvel did
that. And also how that extends to
things like designer architecture. Uh,
Baidu
you acquired a robotics company. And so
it's
>> [laughter]
>> it's less less
>> talked about it too. We just talked
about
>> know. But it's the last time we talked
to me especially in the context of Atlas
like how that maps to robotics. So if
you wouldn't mind just penciling that
out.
>> Yeah, actually Atlas is a
a key part of the puzzle. So,
um,
we acquired this company that was
formerly known as Synnex. And what is
their key technology? Right now their
key technology is a system that goes
from real to sim and and then sim to
real. And what does that mean in robotic
situation? You want to train a robotic
arm to, you know, figure out how to, um,
do cabling, let's say, in a in a
industrial setting. Well, you need a
whole bunch of data to first train a
robotic policy to do these cable cables
cabling activity. And then you want to
evaluate if the robotic policy is doing
a good job. And then you deploy the
robot into the cabling
environment. In order to train, what you
what this company, uh,
Synnex and now our robotics team used to
be doing is doing exactly what Baidu was
saying, dense reconstruction. You take
>> All right, so Synnex
>> pictures of a situation and then and try
to reconstruct that environment. It's
excruciatingly painful. Takes a long
time, laborious, and it really blocks
the velocity of robotic simulation real
to sim, right? So Atlas really is the
next generation technology for that. And
this is not just for robotics cabling or
anything. We should zoom out and
recognize
the biggest problem right now in
robotics is actually data. One day it'll
be chips, but for now it's data. Because
it's so hard to collect real-world data
where robots, you know, are operating
and and uh in order to uh not only you
need to uh collect the data of, let's
say, the cabling situation or
dishwashing situation, whatever. There
is also a very important step called
randomization. Is that you have to take
the same environment and then randomize
the conditions. So, the cable doesn't
literally only, you know, uh bend this
way. It can bend a different way or the
box can have different sizes, colors,
different lids, and all that. And and or
in different parts of the scene. So, you
have to go through a real-to-sim
situation in order to get enough of that
data in addition to other data you can
get from internet. So, this real-to-sim
uh step will be
um
you know, really helped by by Atlas.
That's just the first part of this is
meeting the the the robotics needs in
the current technology cuz we don't yet
have a a frontier foundation model
that's robust enough for for uh
robotics.
But Atlas is a uh omni model. It's a
multi uh multi-modal model. It takes on
different kinds of input and generates
different kind of output. You can
totally imagine the next step is Atlas
um taking in
uh data that's in the
uh in that's dynamical.
And that can really start to
bridge the gap between, you know, action
planning and uh and um
a robotics and and the Atlas output. So,
that's
all narrow map. What are you going to
say something?
>> Yeah, I I was going to say there's
something fundamentally different about
training a robotics policy compared to
really any other application in AI we've
seen before. Um and that's like if
you're generating a piece of code, like
you're generating an image, you're
generating a video, I'm the model is
fundamentally creating this this
artifact. And that artifact like there's
a lot of examples of artifacts that you
can go out on the web or somewhere and
collect. Right? You want to generate
images, there's a lot of images out
there. You want to generate videos,
there's a lot of videos out there. You
want to generate a code base, there's a
lot of code bases out there you can
learn from.
>> Yeah.
>> A robotics policy is something
fundamentally different. It's not
producing a static thing. It's instead a
policy that's going to go out into the
world, make actions, and like try to
achieve a goal. And the world's not
always going to respond the way you
expect, right? Unexpected stuff is going
to happen. So, a robotics policy is like
fundamentally an agent that is out in
the real world interacting with the real
world, and stuff happens. So, you need
like a critical part of that is the
those those policies during training
need to be exposed to every possible
thing that could go wrong during a
deployment. Um and that's where
simulation is really key for robotics,
right? So, there's the then there's two
angles on that. Like one is the kind of
classical simulation. You can go out You
can go and like go to your favorite
physics engine and like try to imagine
creatively as a human designer, what are
all the scenarios that might happen in
this in this in this when achieving this
task, and then try to write explicit
code that models them all. That That's
one angle. And that's an interesting
angle with coding agents. Like that
actually gets supercharged, too. But
there's another angle, which is try to
more data-driven simulation. Right? Like
maybe we can Can we have a learned model
that can understand how the environment
how the world is going to respond to
actions? And maybe it might respond in
unexpected ways sometimes. Then could we
build these neural simulators that are
trained on as much data as we can, then
use these neural simulators, these
learned neural simulators, you know, as
a simulation bed to train robotic
policies.
Um and that's that's a really
interesting future direction of Atlas.
But but then it doesn't stop there,
right?
So
>> [laughter]
>> so um but once you have, you know, this
learned simulator, like this learned
simulator kind of already has in its
like mental brain, like it understands
the world, it understands how the world
is going to respond to actions, and why
doesn't the simulator itself become the
planner? Right? Like the same That's
that's kind of the core thesis that
we've had around world models and their
generality, that there's some core stuff
that a model should understand around
generating worlds, simulating them,
understanding how they appear in
different
situations, and, you know, understanding
how the world's going to respond to an
action is highly related to imagining
what kind of action I need to take to
make the world respond in a particular
way.
>> Yeah.
What what um
one piece of feedback that I got I've
been By the way, congrats on the launch.
It was overwhelmingly positive. I think
it was probably the most significant
model launch this year.
And yeah, everybody said glowing things.
But one person who's an expert in the
space who I texted was like, "What do
you think?" And great person says, "It's
fantastic, it's amazing, but there needs
to be more dynamics."
>> [laughter]
>> And so it would seem to be at least in
the robotics case, but generally it was
kind of ideal to actually have a world
that moves. And so
maybe talk a little bit about that and
then any other future directions that A,
you're comfortable sharing, but you
think are worth talking through.
>> Yeah, I mean, like dynamics is clearly
going to happen. Like actually um
>> We have baby dynamics.
>> We actually do have baby dynamics
already. And this is something I think
people didn't quite appreciate, we
didn't really highlight in the blog
post, but like the previous marble world
model, it was like fundamentally static.
Like the the model just like could not
handle any dynamics at all. And that was
just like baked into the model
architecture, baked into the training,
like the whole thing was fundamentally
static.
>> Yeah.
>> Um we already knew that that was a big
problem post marble, and we already
fixed it in Atlas, right? Like the Atlas
architecture is already fundamentally
supports dynamics. Um the Atlas training
data fundamentally has dynamics. And if
you look carefully in some of the videos
that we've even posted,
>> It actually is.
>> I saw I saw you see that.
>> Yeah, [laughter] the waves, the water
waves.
>> Yeah, so like some of the examples
there's like waves in the water, like in
some of the like air generated aerial
views, there's like little cars moving
around. So like dynamics is actually
already in this model.
>> But is it By the way, dynamics seems
very problematic to me if you're trying
to reconstruct 3D from multiple views,
right? And so like are these things like
at odds or
>> it's actually one of our thesis here is
that like, you know, if you're just
going to do fundamental 3D
reconstruction, you actually want to
have no dynamics. Like you want to be
able to model like exact views of the
scene with exact frozen time.
>> Right.
>> Um, but then like this is actually kind
of a problem with our previous Marble
approach, right? Like there like you can
try to find data that's fully static,
but that's really hard to scale and
really hard to get more of. And the
thing we realized is that even in the
case where I want a static output in the
end, the best way to get it is actually
expose the model to dynamics, right?
Like expose the model to as much dynamic
stuff as you got, as much static stuff
as you got, and let the model figure out
how to factor out the dynamic stuff. So
in especially in like the This is like
>> And this is actually So again, in the
Atlas pre-training already, like it it
saw a ton of dynamics in the
pre-training already. Then the
post-training that we did specific to
this checkpoint in this release was
focused a lot more on on static stuff,
focused a lot more on spatial movement
and less on temporal. But like we
already have we already like I'm pretty
sure this the the the pre-trained
checkpoint already has a lot of latent
dynamics in it.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, and this is something we're going to
improve quite a lot going forward.
>> So so Ben, does that mean we're going to
get 4D video?
You can like go walk around.
>> I mean, I think
>> see the smile on their face. [laughter]
>> So I I I actually can see if like you
just stopped now and you only did kind
of bigger,
you know, faster, better, you could
build almost an entire industry. Like I
feel it feels like a very horizontal
primitive. And then and if you did
nothing else, but are there other things
that are not just kind of bigger, faster
that you're excited about with the
applications you're focused on, which
tend to be kind of more on the kind of
content creator 3D side.
>> Yeah, I'm really excited about pushing
that kind of multimodal aspect. I think
different modes of control is so
critical here. I think like it's super
under appreciated, especially in the
academic community, how critical it is
to add control conditioning to these
models to kind of get out what's inside.
I mean, honestly, this
>> I'm not trying to I don't even
understand what those words
>> So, translate in layman's language is so
editability. I think editability is is
the key here.
>> Yeah, so I mean, this is something we've
seen in like sort of single image models
and starting this year in video models
is starting to be unlocked in terms of
oh, like getting that flavor of like
multi-turn or really like intuitively
interpreting like I want like this
person and this object and this thing to
happen and kind of combining those all
together in like one pastiche without
having to do a lot of like manual work
with the system. Like it just interprets
it like kind of frontier image models
are kind of there, right? For in terms
of editing. But, we haven't seen that
propagate out as strongly into video yet
and then into world models, right? We've
seen some really kind of toy examples of
oh, I can like put in a sentence and
like, you know, a dinosaur appears or
something with these like sort of
real-time models. Um but, I want to like
turn that up to really industrial
strength and make that cuz like the the
trick here is you got to add control,
but not compromise the quality of the
model or it just becomes a a party
trick, basically. Like it's like no one
is going to seriously think about
swapping their like cutting-edge
frontier video model usage for your
model if you give them extra knobs, but
the quality degrades. So, I think it's
really that game of like how can we
maintain maintain like the high bar
we've set with the outputs we're able to
get in the current model and then add
all kinds of interesting stuff that
people will ask us for in terms of like
I want to interact with the scene or
control the layout or control like the
identity of the objects and the things
that we're seeing within there or
control time, right? Um and I think
that's like an axis where it opens up
like a ton of really interesting product
and interface work. The more complexity
you add there and richness in terms of
kind of like enabling you to really
think about like redesigning almost from
scratch the way people interact with
sort of like stateful, you know, 3D
worlds in the computer. Like that's
that's really the end goal here. That is
getting like all the capabilities you
need to build that kind of system.
>> Awesome. Anything to get out of that as
far as new functionality that you'd be
excited about that's not just bigger
better?
>> I think for me, let's go back to the
first principle of intelligence.
Intelligence is not sitting there stuck
and just seeing something or
interpreting something when it comes to
space and physical space, right? It's
really this uh closing the loop between
seeing and experiencing and interaction.
So, just thinking about going up that
ladder is exactly what uh Ben said.
>> Cool. I think one interesting notion
there is this notion of AI completeness.
>> You heard of that before?
>> Yeah, yeah, I have. Yeah.
>> So, like everyone
>> Yeah, I I hear about AI complete, by the
way, in terms of LLMs, which is like you
have to be basically, you know, like the
smartest LLM to answer the question what
the smartest LLM will need to answer or
you have to solve general intelligence.
>> No, no, it's it's basically it's it's a
connection to Turing completeness,
right? Like the idea being that like
a task is Turing complete like in
classical complexity theory if like I
can take any class of any problem in
this category, reduce to that one
problem, right? Three SAT is a classic
example, right? So, you can take any
NP-hard problem and reduce it to three
SAT. Therefore, therefore, you can use
three SAT to solve any any problem.
>> Yeah, it's it's a yeah, yeah.
>> So, so then like the the kind of like
soft definition of AI completeness is
like there's this fundamental primitive
that's that's an AI task, but if I could
solve this AI task in its full broadest
generality
>> You solve that.
>> it would solve any intelligence problem.
And like the classic example of LLMs is
like next token prediction is AI
complete because I could like, you know,
there's the classic example, I think
from Ilya, where like I there's a
mystery novel and like the thing has to
read the whole mystery novel and the
final sentence of the mystery novel is
like, "And the killer was Predict the
[laughter] next token.
So, like you could basically like frame
any kind of intelligence task in terms
of that. So, clearly next token
prediction is something that people
believe is AI complete.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> But I think that something we're kind of
realizing and Ben was uh talking about
this earlier today is like new view
prediction, this primitive that we have
in Atlas, especially generative new new
view new view prediction. This is also
AI complete. Right? And because I could
take something like
>> You could you could have the the movie
and you do all of the frames of the
movie and then like the killer walks out
and then you predict exactly who walks
out.
>> [laughter]
>> Exactly. Not just that, but I could say
like
I want to have a world where like
Martine is like writing a proof of the
Riemann hypothesis on the
>> So
okay, so to take a evolutionary view,
right? That new viewpoint prediction is
exactly evolution had to solve by making
animals move.
You you nature give animals eyes.
But nature didn't give trees eye.
Eyes. Why? Because when you move, you
see a new viewpoint. And that is the the
the whether you call it AI complete or
intelligence complete. So So we do
believe very strongly that next
viewpoint prediction is is the
equivalent of next token prediction.
>> Amazing.
Well, with that, congratulations all of
you on a phenomenal model launch. We're
very excited for future model launches
and thanks for coming.
>> Thank you.